Back in New York, I am the head of development
في نيويورك انا رئيس تطوير
for a non-profit called Robin Hood.
لمجموعة غير ربحية تدعى روبن هون
When I'm not fighting poverty, I'm fighting fires
ولكني لا احارب الفقر .. بل احارب الحرائق
as the assistant captain of a volunteer fire company.
كمساعد كابتن في شركة اطفاء تطوعية
Now in our town,
في مدينتنا
where the volunteers supplement a highly skilled career staff,
حيث ان المتطوعين يملكون مهارات عالية جداً
you have to get to the fire scene pretty early
عليك ان تسارع بالوصول الى موقع الحريق بسرعة كبيرة
to get in on any action.
لكي تشارك في الاطفاء
I remember my first fire.
واتذكر الحريق الاول الذي شاركت في اخماده
I was the second volunteer on the scene,
كنت حينها ثاني المتطوعين الذين يصلون الى الموقع
so there was a pretty good chance I was going to get in.
وكان هناك فرصة جيدة بأن اشارك بالعملية
But still it was a real footrace against the other volunteers
وحينها حدث سباق جري بين المتطوعين
to get to the captain in charge
للوصول الى الكابتن المسؤول
to find out what our assignments would be.
عن توزيع المهام لكي يحصلوا على مهمة مميزة
When I found the captain,
وعندما وصلت الى الكابتن
he was having a very engaging conversation
كان يتحادث بصورة جدلية
with the homeowner,
مع صاحبة المنزل
who was surely having one of the worst days of her life.
والتي كانت تواجه لا محالة اسوء ايام حياتها
Here it was, the middle of the night,
فقد كانت تقف في منتصف الليل
she was standing outside in the pouring rain,
والامطار تهطل بغزارة
under an umbrella, in her pajamas, barefoot,
ومعها مظلة .. وملابس النوم .. بأقدام عارية
while her house was in flames.
بينما كان منزلها تلتهمه النيران
The other volunteer who had arrived just before me --
كان المتطوع الذي وصل قبلي ..
let's call him Lex Luther --
ولندعوه " ليكس لوثر "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
got to the captain first
كان قد كُلف بالمهمة الاولى
and was asked to go inside
فقد طلب منه الدخول الى المنزل
and save the homeowner's dog.
لانقاذ كلب صاحبة المنزل
The dog! I was stunned with jealousy.
الكلب ! نعم .. لقد وقفت والغيرة تتملكني
Here was some lawyer or money manager
لان المتطوع ذاك والذي كان محامياً او محاسباً
who, for the rest of his life, gets to tell people
سوف يتحدث طيلة حياته
that he went into a burning building
عن كيفية اقتحامه لمبنى محترق
to save a living creature,
لكي ينقذ كائناً حياً
just because he beat me by five seconds.
فقط لانه هزمني بالوصول الى الكابتن بخمس ثوان
Well, I was next.
لابأس .. حان دوري بعده ..
The captain waved me over.
فلوح المدرب الي ..
He said, "Bezos, I need you to go into the house.
وقال " بيزوس " اريدك ان تدخل الى المنزل
I need you to go upstairs, past the fire,
وان تصعد الى الطابق العلوي .. مخترقاً النيران
and I need you to get this woman a pair of shoes."
وان تحذر لهذه المرأة زوجي أحذية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I swear.
أقسم لكم !
So, not exactly what I was hoping for,
لم يكن هذا ما أرجوه حقاً
but off I went --
ولكني انطلقت
up the stairs, down the hall, past the 'real' firefighters,
صعدت السلالم .. وتجاوزت رجال الاطفاء الحقيقين
who were pretty much done putting out the fire at this point,
الذين كانوا على وشك اخماد النيران حقاً في تلك الآونة
into the master bedroom to get a pair of shoes.
ودخلت الى غرفة النوم الرئيسية .. واحضرت لها زوجي أحذية
Now I know what you're thinking,
والآن انا أعي مالذي يجول في خاطركم
but I'm no hero.
أنني لست بطلاً !
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I carried my payload back downstairs
لقد حملت حمولتي - الاحذية -
where I met my nemesis
حيث قابلت غريمي ..
and the precious dog by the front door.
وهو حاملاً الكلب على باب المنزل
We took our treasures outside to the homeowner,
واخذنا كنوزنا وذهبنا الى مالكة المنزل
where, not surprisingly,
حيث لم أتفاجىء
his received much more attention than did mine.
ان كنز غريمي قد نال الكثير من الاهتمام اكثر من كنزي ..
A few weeks later,
بعد عدة اسابيع
the department received a letter from the homeowner
تلقت المنظمة .. رسالة من صاحبة المنزل
thanking us for the valiant effort displayed
تشكر فيها الجهود المبذولة ذلك اليوم
in saving her home.
في انقاذ منزلها
The act of kindness she noted above all others:
واشارت الى حدث لطيف استقطب إهتمامها اكثر من أي شئ
someone had even gotten her a pair of shoes.
حيث قالت .. "لقد اخترق احدهم النيران .. وجلب لي أحذيتي"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In both my vocation at Robin Hood
ان في عملي لدى روبن هود ..
and my avocation as a volunteer firefighter,
او كرجل اطفاء متطوع
I am witness to acts of generosity and kindness
شهدت الكثير من الطيبة والكرم
on a monumental scale,
على صعيد واسع جداً
but I'm also witness to acts of grace and courage
ولكني ايضاً شهدت الكثير من الشجاعة و السمو
on an individual basis.
على المستويات الشخصية
And you know what I've learned?
وأتعلمون مالذي تعلمته ؟
They all matter.
ان لكل شيء أهمية ما !
So as I look around this room
و ها أنا انظر الآن الى هذه الغرفة
at people who either have achieved,
على أشخاص حققوا
or are on their way to achieving,
أو على وشك ان يحققوا
remarkable levels of success,
نجاحاً باهراً في حياتهم على عدة مستويات
I would offer this reminder:
أريد ان أذكركم فحسب :
don't wait.
لا تنتظروا !
Don't wait until you make your first million
لا تنتظروا حصولكم على المليون الاول
to make a difference in somebody's life.
لكي تحدثوا فرقاً في حياة شخص ما ..
If you have something to give,
ان كنت تملك شيئاً يمكنك تقديمه ..
give it now.
قدمه الآن
Serve food at a soup kitchen. Clean up a neighborhood park.
صب الحساء لشخص يقف بقربك في المطعم .. نظف حديقة جارك ..
Be a mentor.
كن مرشداً ..
Not every day is going to offer us a chance
لن تملك الفرصة لذلك كل يوم ..
to save somebody's life,
لن تملك فرصة انقاذ حياة شخص ما كل يوم ..
but every day offers us an opportunity to affect one.
ولكنك كل يوم تملك فرصة التأثير بحياة شخص ما ..
So get in the game. Save the shoes.
لذا .. انخرط في الحياة .. أنقذ الاحذية !
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Mark, Mark, come back.
برونو جيوساني : مارك .. مارك .. عد
Mark Bezos: Thank you.
مارك بيزوس : شكرا لكم